[Music]
The Society for Sarcopenia Cexium
wasting disease convened an expert panel
that despite the lack of long-term
trials suggested creatine be used for
the management of age- related muscle
loss also known as sarcopenia.
Are there any creatine side effects?
Well, if one can extrapolate from mice,
one side effect may be longevity. The
average healthy lifespan of creatine-fed
mice was found to be 9% more than
control mice, and they performed better
on neurobbehavioral tests, especially
improved memory skills. But is taking
creatine safe? One can take a bit of
comfort in the fact that it's one of the
world's bestselling dietary supplements
with literally billions of servings
taken, and the only consistently
reported side effect has been weight
gain, presumed to be from water
retention. The only serious side effects
appear to be among those with
pre-existing kidney diseases taking
whopping doses of like 20 grams a day
for weeks. The bottom line, according to
the European Food Safety Authority, is
that doses of up to three grams a day
are unlikely to pose any risk, provided
high purity creatine is used. Dietary
supplements are not regulated by the FDA
and may not actually contain what's on
the label or in the case of creatine be
tainted with contaminants generated
during the industrial production
process. When researchers looked at 33
samples of creatine supplements made in
the US and Europe, they all did actually
contain creatine. That's good. But half
exceeded the maximum level recommended
by food safety authorities for at least
one contaminant. The researchers
recommend that consumers choose products
from producers that ensure the highest
quality control, but that's easier said
than done.
One third-party supplement testing
outfit that tested for purities chose
Bulk Supplements brand as their top
pick, which also happened to be the
cheapest at about 10 cents per daily 5 g
serving, which is a level teaspoon. What
about just getting it from meat? You
could get that three grams of creatine
eating about five steaks a day since
cooking destroys about 20%. But the heat
reacts with the creatine and amino acids
in meat to create carcinogenic
heteroscyclic amines. One of the reasons
meat is considered to be cancer-causing.
A separate safety concern was raised
that creatine in supplement form could
potentially form a different carcinogen
known as nitrosarazine when it hit the
acid bath of the stomach. But when
actually put to the test, this does not
appear to be a problem.
Some have argued caution for creatine
use among those with kidney issues. This
concern appears to derive in part from a
misinterpretation
of laboratory data. The blood levels of
a different compound called creatinin is
used as a marker of kidney function.
It's a muscle metabolism waste product
that is regularly cleared out by well
functioning kidneys. So if your levels
rise, maybe your kidneys aren't doing so
good. But where does creatinin come
from? the breakdown of creatine. So if
you take extra creatine, your creatinin
levels in your blood could rise, giving
the false impression that your kidneys
are malfunctioning, but instead you're
just making more rather than clearing
less. For patients who take creatine,
doctors can consider other kidney
function tests such as blood levels of
statin C levels, a waste product that's
more independent of dietary
intervention. So tell your health care
professional if you start creatine.
Overall, creatine supplementation
appears to be safe for the kidneys, but
the longest study to date is less than 3
years. So, true long-term studies are
lacking.
[Music]